Rhiannon: Puberty can be a challenging
time as hormones kick in and children
develop new moods and feelings
and the "emotional rollercoaster"
they're on, can have real lasting
psychological effects, The physical
changes give rise to a variety of
social and emotional changes as well,
directly affecting the body and brain.
They start to look and act
differently, and an array of social
influences further accelerate
these social and emotional changes.
Leah: As their bodies change, they
may experience a new and unfamiliar
set of social experiences and become
interested in forming what can become
intense, romantic, and sometimes
sexualised relationships with others
and they may be start to become
treated by society differently.
Those who mature quickly may be more
popular than those who mature slowly.
Adults may also view them differently
expecting more adult behaviour, when
they are still more or less a child.
Rhiannon: Body dissatisfaction
has been linked to depression and
anxiety particularly in children
who do not match the ‘ideal body’.
Young people who are overweight can have
lower self-esteem than their peers and may
look to weight control options, such as
using diet pills, diuretics and laxatives.
Leah: Children and young people with poor
body image are less likely to take part
in physical activities due to worries
about their appearance, this can therefore
compound their possible health issues.
Whilst those with good body image are
less likely to diet or use alcohol or
cigarettes, increasing the chance of more
positive mental health and well-being.
Rhiannon: While body image concerns
affect both boys and girls, more girls
are likely to be dissatisfied with
their appearance and their weight
and more likely to consider going on
a diet or having cosmetic surgery.
Whereas boys are less likely but
might be more inclined to look
at using steroids to bulk up.
These behaviours can be the start
of further mental health problems.
Leah: Young women often report feeling
a pressure to be thin, but to still
maintain curves, especially when they
see how ‘the ideal’ is portrayed on
social media, therefore they may look to
having procedures to enhance themselves.
Young men often report pressure to
be tall and more muscular so may hit
the gym, start lifting wights and
bulking up naturally or using steroids.
Rhiannon: How young people develop their
sense of ‘ideal’ appearance is varied.
Young people themselves identify
the media, pressure from family and
friends, comparisons with peers,
and personal factors like low
self-esteem, feelings of depression,
and a need for control, as important
influences on their own body image.
We need to be mindful of all of these
factors to potentially counter some of
the negative affects they can have on
children and young people’s mental health.